A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Governance and Public Policy (GPP), Office Files of June Zeitlin and William Diaz FA543
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Governance and Public Policy (GPP), Office Files of June Zeitlen and William Diaz
1983-1995, bulk 1993-1995
1993-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
Diaz, William A.
Zeitlin, June H.
Ford Foundation
FA543
1.31 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series:
1. June Zeitlen.
2. William Diaz.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence and memoranda.
Biographical / Historical
Throughout her career, June Zeitlin has worked as a foundation executive, women's rights lawyer, and public policy expert. She held a number of different positions related to human rights, women's rights, public policy, and governance from 1986 to 1999 at the Ford Foundation. The Foundation originally hired her as a Program Officer in the Human Rights and Governance Program. Following a change to the Foundation's program structure for human rights support, she became Deputy Director for the Rights and Social Justice Program. In this position, she was responsible for managing grants for women's rights and opportunities. Then in 1993, she became Director of the Governance and Public Policy Program and retained her Director responsibilities when that program transitioned to become Governance and Civil Society.
Zeitlin graduated from the University of Rochester in 1970 with a B.A. in political science. She then earned her law degree from New York University in 1973. Prior to her work at the Ford Foundation, she held a variety of government and legal advocacy jobs in Washington D.C. and New York City. Some of these jobs included Legislative Assistant to Representative Bella Abzurg (1975-1977), Director of the Office on Domestic Violence in the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (1979-1981), Attorney for the National Women's Law Center (1981-1982), and Director of the Office of Legislative Coordination for the New York City Human Resources Administration (1982-1985) among others.
After leaving the Ford Foundation in 1999, Zeitlin became Executive Director of the Women's Environment and Development Organization (WEDO). She stayed in that position until 2008 and later served as Director for the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW) Education Project at The Leadership Conference on Civil and Human Rights.
Biographical / Historical
William Diaz was a foundation program officer and university professor. He worked as a program officer at the Ford Foundation for over 10 years.
Diaz joined the Ford Foundation in 1982 as a Program Officer in the Foundation's Human Rights and Governance Program (HRG). He was the Foundation's first Latino Program Officer. In 1984, he wrote the working paper "Hispanics: Challenges and Opportunities". The paper described the demographic, economic, social, and political circumstances of Hispanic people in the United States and discussed the Ford Foundation's initiatives for addressing the needs of the growing Hispanic population. Following an organizational change in the Foundation's programming, Diaz became a Program Officer in the Governance and Public Policy Program (GPP) in 1991. He stayed in that position until he left the Foundation.
Diaz's post-Ford Foundation career included his positions as a Senior Fellow and professor at the University of Minnesota's Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs. Diaz completed his undergraduate education at Fordham University. He also earned his M.S. and Ph.D. from the university. He died in 2002.
- June Zeitlin, 1993-1995; I
  - Correspondence/Memoranda, 1993 November-1994 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda, 1994 March-October (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1994 March-1995 May (Box 1)
  - Memoranda, 1994 December-1995 May (Box 1)
- William Diaz, 1983-1993; II
  - Meetings File, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation Minority Training Programs, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Hispanics - Challenes and Opportunities - Background, 1983-1993 (Box 1)
  - Diversity Cases, 1992 (Box 1)